Finding Aid for Arthur Pound Papers 1928-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur Pound Papers 1928-1968
Pound, Arthur, 1884-1966.
1 linear feet
Historical writer. Correspondence, drafts of works, research materials, and copies of articles; include draft of book on Lake Ontario, research materials on the RCA corporation and radio broadcasting, research materials on the history of General Motors; manuscript on the state of American society probably 1941, written by California Senator Sheridan Downey.
85522 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Arthur Pound (donor no 2356) in multiple accessions, 1947-1962 and by his daughter Madelon Graves (donor no. 4678 ) in different accessions, 1969-1978.
The collection is open for research.
Arthur Pound, June 1, 1884 - Jan. 14, 1966, was born in Pontiac, Michigan. He worked for a variety of newspapers as an editor and editorial writer between 1913 and 1940. In 1935 and 1936 Pound was a research professor of American history at the University of Pittsburgh. From 1940 to 1944 Pound served as state historian and Director of the Division of Archives and History for New York. Pound is the author of The Iron Man in Industry, 1922; Johnson of the Mohawks, (with Richard E. Day), 1930; Hawk of Detroit, 1939; Detroit: Dynamic City, 1940; and Lake Ontario, 1945, among other works. He was also co-editor, with Samuel Taylor Moore, of They Told Barron, 1930; and More They Told Barron, 1931.
The Arthur Pound collection includes correspondence, drafts of works, research notes, and copies of articles written by Pound. The material dates from 1928 to 1968. The correspondence, almost exclusively incoming, relates primarily to Pound's professional career and includes letters relating to the publication of Lake Ontario, They Told Barron, and More They Told Barron. The collection also contains a complete early draft of Lake Ontario and a manuscript of a work apparently submitted to Pound for his comments. This manuscript was labeled as "Senator Downey's MSS" and is probably the work of Sheridan Downey, U.S. Senator from California, 1939-1950. The work gives Downey's analysis of American society and appears to have been written in 1941.
The research material generated during Pound's work on the history of the RCA Corporation has been retained to illustrate his research techniques. An early draft of a chapter titled "Broadcasting" is included in the collection. A folder of photographs showing RCA facilities and personnel has been transferred to the library's photographic department. The collection also contains incomplete notes from Pound's works Johnson of the Mohawks, More They Told Barron, and a history of General Motors. There are also in the Pound collection research and travel notes from 1936, a notebook containing newsclippings and acknowledgements of gift copies of Detroit: Dynamic City, several contracts, and a small amount of financial material.
Subjects:
Automobile industry and trade--United States.; Downey, Sheridan.; General Motors Corporation.; Ontario, Lake (N.Y. and Ont.); Pound, Arthur, 1884-1966.; Radio broadcasting--United States.; Radio Corporation of America.
- Correspondence
  - 1928-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942 (Box 1)
  - 1943 (Box 1)
  - January-October 1944 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1968 (Box 1)
- Writings and Research materials
  - Lake Ontario
    - Drafts
      - Chapter One (Box 1)
      - Chapter Two (Box 1)
      - Chapter Three (Box 1)
      - Chapter Four (Box 1)
      - Chapter Five (Box 1)
      - Prelude to Revolution (Box 1)
      - Niagara Colony and Last of the Border Raids (Box 1)
      - Saratoga and Consequences (Box 1)
      - Sullivan's Raid (Box 1)
      - Carlton's Island (Box 1)
      - Quebec Act (Box 1)
    - Lake Ontario (comments and criticisms) (Box 1)
  - RCA historical research materials
    - Notes and drafts
      - Introduction (Box 1)
      - Tubes (Box 1)
      - Communications, Antennas (Box 1)
      - Television (Box 1)
      - Radar and Facsimile (Box 1)
      - FM (Box 1)
      - Sound (Box 1)
      - Aviation, Drive (Box 1)
      - Missiles (Box 1)
      - Infra Red (Box 1)
      - Post War (Box 1)
      - The Fourth Chime (annotated book on NBC) (Box 1)
      - The Fourth Chime (notes and revisions) (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous notes, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - "Broadcasting"-drafts of chapters
      - Introduction (Box 1)
      - NBC International (Box 1)
      - NBC University of the Air (Box 1)
      - The Army Hour (Box 1)
      - News and Special Events (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1)
  - General Motors history, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Johnson of the Mohawks (Box 1)
    include illustrative material
  - Barron books (Box 1)
  - Re. George Eastman (Box 1)
  - Research and travel notes (Box 1)
  - Other research materials
    - Newsclippings and acknowledgements re. Detroit: Dynamic City (Box 1)
    - Pound articles, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Articles collected by Pound (Box 1)
    - Flyers for books written by Pound (Box 1)
    - Contracts and financial material circa 1931-1942 (Box 1)
  - "Senator Downey's MSS"
    (probably the work of Sheridan Downey on the state of American society, 1941)
    - Chapter 1. Double Defense (Box 1)
    - Chapter 2. Coming Collapse (Box 1)
    - Chapter 3. Excursion in Economics (Box 1)
    - Chapter 4. Business Begins to Save (Box 1)
    - Chapter 5. An Economist Testifies (Box 1)
    - Chapter 6. A Billion is a Lot of Money (Box 1)
    - Chapter 7. Let's Talk About Taxes (Box 1)
    - Chapter 8. Social Philosophy (Box 1)
    - Chapter 9. The Big, Bad Debt (Box 1)
    - Chapter 10. An Engineer on the Stand; Chapter 11. Roads (Box 1)
    - Epilogue (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Guest book (Madelon Pound House) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)